Guide to the Inside-Outside Alliance records, 2012-2019 and undated RL.11478
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Inside-Outside Alliance records
2012-2019 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Inside-Outside Alliance
RL.11478
2.25 Linear Feet
0.08 Gigabytes
Collection includes zines, newsletters, flyers, posters, banners, and a petition which document Inside-Outside Alliance's activism concerning the Durham County Jail and policing in Durham, North Carolina. This collection also documents the stories of Durham County Jail detainees and community members.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into the following series: Printed Materials, Ephemera and Objects, and Social Media. Materials are arranged alphabetically within the series.
Biographical / Historical
Inside-Outside Alliance (IOA) was a political organization trying to support the struggles of those inside (or formerly inside) Durham County jail, and their families and friends. Based in Durham, North Carolina, IOA was a diverse, multi-generational group that welcomed children of all ages and their caregivers and that sought bold, strategic ways to disrupt the justice system and challenge the idea that police and prisons exist to keep us safe. Since 2012, IOA worked to support prisoners in the Durham County jail and to fight police terrorism throughout the city. Rather than lobbying or endorsing political action, IOA communicated with prisoners and former prisoners of the Durham County Jail and published their writing and art through the print publication Feedback, as well as their website, amplifyvoices.com and social media. IOA also participated in struggles against police harassment and brutality by coordinating public protests and demonstrations. IOA disbanded in Spring 2019.
[text excerpted and edited from amplifyvoices.com with permission of IOA]
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Inside-Outside Alliance records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2017 and 2020.
Scope and Contents
Collection includes zines, newsletters in physical and digital forms, banners, posters, fliers, and a petition which document Inside-Outside Alliance's activism concerning the Durham County Jail and policing in Durham, North Carolina. Banners protest video visitation policy and oppose the presence of ICE in Durham, N.C. Posters list names of those who died in custody. This collection also documents the stories of Durham County Jail detainees and community members.
Social movements -- United States; Protest movements -- United States; Imprisonment; Human rights advocacy -- United States; Inmates of institutions -- North Carolina -- Durham -- Death; Inmates of institutions -- Abuse of -- North Carolina -- Durham; Law enforcement -- United States; Prisoners -- Correspondence; Newsletters; Fliers (printed matter); petitions; Durham (N.C.); Zines; Jails -- North Carolina -- Durham; Videoconferencing; Prison visits -- Durham (N.C.); Prisoners -- Death; Human Rights Archive (Duke University); Durham (N.C.) -- Police Department; United States.. Bureau of Immigration and Customs Enforcement.
- Printed Materials, 2012-2018 and undated
  Scope and Contents
  Includes zines, physical and digital (PDF format) newsletters, fliers, and a petition that document the organization's activism concerning the Durham County Jail and policing in Durham, North Carolina. These materials also document the stories of Durham County community members and jail detainees. Additionally, this series documents the deaths of Jesus Chuy Huerte and Matthew McCain, who died while in police custody.
  - Amplifiyvoices.com article, "Durham Jail Attempts to Cover Up a Death by Medical Neglect...", 2016 January 22 (Box 1)
    Re: death of Matthew McCain
  - feedback: voices inside, amplified, 2013-2017; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - feedback: voices inside, amplified and feedback: voices from the jail struggle, 2013-2018; 50 digital files; approximately 80 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL11478-SET-0001)
    The newsletter underwent a change in subtitle in 2015. Between 2013 and 2015, the title was feedback: voices inside, amplified. After 2015, the title was feedback: voices from the jail struggle.
  - Fliers, undated (Box 1)
    Fliers in English and Spanish that document letter writing campaigns, protests, outreach, and Durham County jail policies (such as requiring a state-issued ID for visitors to the jail and banning pencils among inmates).
  - Inside-Outside News/Las Noticias Dentro y Afuera, 2015-2017 (Box 1)
    Newsletter published by Inside-Outside Alliance that covers Durham County jail inmate experiences, various aspects of jail and prison privatization, methods of involvement with IOA (weekly protests, meeting times, letter writing, committees), and legal and political conflicts related to police brutality and incarceration.
  - Justice for Chuy/Justicia para Chuy, 2013 (Box 1)
    Pamphlet and flier relating to Jesus Chuy Huerte who died while in Durham police custody on November 19, 2013.
  - Petition and demands addressed to the Durham County Sheriff's Department, 2012-2015 (Box 1)
- Websites and Social Media, 2017-2019
  Series consists of web content created by the Inside-Outside Alliance on three platforms: the group's website on WordPress, a Facebook page, and a Twitter page. The websites were harvested using the Internet Archive's Archive-It service between 2017 and 2019. Content from prior to 2017 is likely accessible through these harvests.
  - Inside-Outside Alliance website, 2017-2019
  - Inside-Outside Alliance Facebook page, 2017-2019
  - Inside-Outside Alliance Twitter page, 2017-2019
- Ephemera and Objects, 2019
  - Posters originally held during protests outside Durham County Jail, 2019 (Box 2)
    Assorted handmade and printed posters protesting jail's treatment of inmates and directing viewers to AmplifyVoices.com. Includes a poster listing names of people who died while in Durham Police custody: Niecey Fennell, Matthew McCain, Dennis McMurray, Raphael Bennett, Terry Lee, and DaShawn Evans.
  - Cloth banners from Durham County Jail protests, 2019 (Box 2)
    Banner (black fabric, white text): "'Video visit' is Newspeak." Banner (white fabric, black and red text): "Video visitation is not visitation at all." Banner (white fabric, black and red text): "ICE out of Durham / Video =/= Visitation / No more jail deaths / IOA [heart] Alerta."